<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A chaine of pearle. Or A memoriall of the peerles graces, and heroick vertues of Queene Elizabeth, of glorious memory. Composed by the noble lady, Diana Primrose</title>
            <author>Primrose, Diana.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837015</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 971:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A chaine of pearle. Or A memoriall of the peerles graces, and heroick vertues of Queene Elizabeth, of glorious memory. Composed by the noble lady, Diana Primrose</title>
                  <author>Primrose, Diana.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Dawson] for Thomas Paine, and are to be sold by Philip Waterhouse, at his shop at the signe of St. Pauls-head in Canning-street neere London-stone,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A chaine of pearle, or A memoriall of Queene Elizabeth.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Chaine of Pearle. <hi>OR</hi> A Memoriall of the peerles Graces, and Heroick Vertues of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of Glorious Memory.</p>
            <p>Compoſed by the Noble Lady, <hi>Diana Primroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Dat ROSA mel apibus, quâ ſugit ARANEA virus.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Paine,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Philip Waterhouſe,</hi> at his ſhop at the ſigne of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
<hi>Pauls-head</hi> in <hi>Canning-ſtreet neere London-ſtone.</hi>
1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL NOBLE LADIES, and <hi>GENTLE-WOMEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O You the Honour of our Noble Sex,</l>
            <l>I ſend this <hi>CHAINE,</hi> with all my beſt Reſpects:</l>
            <l>Which if you pleaſe to weare, for her ſweet ſake,</l>
            <l>For whom I did this ſlender <hi>POEM</hi> make.</l>
            <l>You ſhall erect a Trophie to her Name,</l>
            <l>And crowne your ſelues with neuer-fading Fame.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Devoted to your Vertues,</hi> DIANA P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE EXCELLENT LADY,</hi> the Compoſer of this Worke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hine forth <hi>(Diana)</hi> dart thy Golden Raies,</l>
               <l>On Her bleſt Life and Raigne, whoſe Noble Praiſe</l>
               <l>Deſerues a Quill pluckt from an Angels wing,</l>
               <l>And none to write it but a Crowned King.</l>
               <l>Shee, Shee it was, that gaue vs Golden Daies,</l>
               <l>And did the Engliſh Name to Heauen raiſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bleſt be her Name! bleſt be her Memory!</l>
               <l>That <hi>England</hi> crown'd with ſuch Felicity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And Thou, the <hi>Prime-Roſe</hi> of the <hi>Muſes</hi> nine,</l>
               <l>(In whoſe ſweete Verſe <hi>ELIZA</hi>'S Fame doth ſhine,</l>
               <l>Like ſome reſplendent Star in froſty night)</l>
               <l>Haſt made thy Natiue Splendor far more bright;</l>
               <l>Since all thy <hi>PEARLES</hi> are peerles-orient,</l>
               <l>And to thy ſelfe a precious Ornament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is my cenſure of thy <hi>ROYALL CHAINE</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which a far better Cenſure well may claime.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>
               <hi>DOROTHY BERRY.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:4"/>
            <head>THE INDVCTION.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Golden Phaebus with his radiant face</l>
               <l>Enthron'd in his Triumphant Chaire of State,</l>
               <l>The twinkling Stars and Asteriſmes doth chafe</l>
               <l>With his Imperiall Scepter, and doth hate</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All Conſorts in his Starry Monarchy,</l>
               <l>As preiudiciall to his Soveraignty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So Great <hi>ELIZA,</hi> Englands brighteſt Sun,</l>
               <l>The Worlds Renowne and everlasting Lampe,</l>
               <l>Admits not here the leaſt Compariſon;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Glories, doe the Greateſt Princes dampe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ever Scepter ſwai'd or Crowne did weare,</l>
               <l>Within the Verge of either Hemiſpheare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou Engliſh Goddeſſe, Empreſſe of our Sex,</l>
               <l>O Thou whoſe Name ſtill raignes in all our hearts,</l>
               <l>To whom are due, our ever-vowd Respects!</l>
               <l>How ſhall I blazon thy moſt Royall parts?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which in all Parts did ſo divinely ſhine,</l>
               <l>As they deſerue <hi>Apollo's</hi> Quili (not mine.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet, ſince the <hi>GODS</hi> accept the humble Vowes</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1319:4"/>
               <l>Of Mortalls; daigne (O Thou Star-crowned Queene)</l>
               <l>T' accept theſe ill-compoſed Pearly-Rowes:</l>
               <l>Wherein, thy Glory chieflty ſhall be ſeene:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For by theſe Lines ſo blacke and impolite,</l>
               <l>Thy Swan-like Lustre ſhall appeare more white.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Emperiall Majeſties eternall Votary, <hi>DIANA.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1319:5"/>
            <head>A CHAINE OF PEARLE, <hi>OR</hi> A Memoriall of Q.
<hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="religion" type="part">
               <head>The firſt Pearle. <hi>RELIGION.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE goodlieſt Pearle in faire <hi>Eliza's</hi> Chaine;</l>
               <l>Is true Religion, which did chiefly gaine</l>
               <l>A Royall Luſtre to the reſt, and ti'de</l>
               <l>The Hearts of <hi>ALL</hi> to her when <hi>Mary</hi> di'de.</l>
               <l>And though Shee found the Realme infected much</l>
               <l>With Superſtition, and Abuſes, ſuch</l>
               <l>As (in all humane Iudgement) could not be</l>
               <l>Reform'd without domeſticke Mutiny,</l>
               <l>And great Hoſtility from Spaine and France;</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>SHEE</hi> vndaunted, brauely did advance</l>
               <l>Chriſts Glorious Enſigne, maugre all the Feares</l>
               <l>Or Dangers which appear'd: and for ten yeares</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1319:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>SHEE</hi> ſwaid the Scepter with a Ladies hand,</l>
               <l>Not vrging any Romiſt in the Land,</l>
               <l>By ſharpe Edicts the Temple to frequent,</l>
               <l>Or to partake the holy Sacrament.</l>
               <l>But factious Romaniſts not thus content,</l>
               <l>Their Agents to their holy Fatherſent,</l>
               <l>Deſiring him, by ſollemne Bull, proclaime</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> an Heretike, and name</l>
               <l>Some other Soveraigne, which might erect</l>
               <l>Their masking Maſſe, and hence forthwith eject</l>
               <l>The Evangelicall Profeſſion,</l>
               <l>Which flouriſht vnder her Protection.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> to this Petition condeſcends,</l>
               <l>And ſoone his Leaden Bull to England ſends,</l>
               <l>Which by one <hi>FELTON,</hi> on the Biſhops Gate</l>
               <l>Of London was affixed; But the <hi>STATE</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For that high Treaſon puniſht him with death,</l>
               <l>That would dethrone his Queene, <hi>ELIZABETH.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet was this Ball of Wild-fire working ſtill,</l>
               <l>In many Romaniſts which had a will,</l>
               <l>The preſent State and Governement to change;</l>
               <l>That they in all Idolatrie might range.</l>
               <l>And hence it came that Great <hi>Northumberland,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aſſociate with Earle of <hi>Westmerland,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And many moe, their Banners did diſplay</l>
               <l>In open Field; hoping to win the Day.</l>
               <l>Againſt theſe Rebells, Noble <hi>SVSSEX</hi> went;</l>
               <l>And ſoone their bloudy Purpoſe did prevent.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> fled, <hi>Northumberland</hi> did die,</l>
               <l>For that ſoule Crime, and deepe diſloyalty;</l>
               <l>Having engaged Thouſands in that Cauſe.</l>
               <l>After which time, the <hi>QVEENE</hi> made ſtricter Lawes.</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1319:6"/>
               <l>Againſt Recuſants; and with Lyons heart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee</hi> bang'd the <hi>Pope,</hi> and tooke the Goſpells part.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> perceiving that his Bull was baited</l>
               <l>In ſuch rude ſort, and all his hopes defeated:</l>
               <l>Cries out to Spaine for helpe; who takes occaſion</l>
               <l>Thereby t'attempt the Conqueſt of this Nation.</l>
               <l>But ſuch Sage Counſellers <hi>ELIZA</hi> had;</l>
               <l>As, though both Spaine<note n="*" place="margin">In vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam rabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em fure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> converſi.</note> and Rome were almoſt mad</l>
               <l>For griefe and anger, yet they ſtill did faile,</l>
               <l>And againſt England never could prevaile.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="chastity" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Pearle. <hi>CHASTITY.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE next faire Pearle that comes in order here,</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> wherein <hi>SHEE</hi> had no peere.</l>
                  <l>Mongſt all the Noble Princeſſes which then</l>
                  <l>In Europe were the Royall <hi>Anadem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And though for Beauty <hi>SHEE</hi> an Angell was,</l>
                  <l>And all our Sex did there in farre ſurpaſſe;</l>
                  <l>Yet did her pure vnſpotted <hi>Chaſtitie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her heavenly Beautie rarely beautifie.</l>
                  <l>How many Kings and Princes did aſpire,</l>
                  <l>To win her Loue? In whom that Veſtall Fire</l>
                  <l>Still flaming, never would <hi>Shee</hi> condeſcend</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Hymen's</hi> Rihtes, though much <hi>Shee</hi> did commend,</l>
                  <l>That braue French <hi>MONSIEVR</hi> who did hope to carry</l>
                  <l>The Golden fleece, and faire <hi>ELIZA</hi> marry.</l>
                  <l>Yea Spaniſh <hi>PHILIP,</hi> Husband to her Siſter,</l>
                  <l>Was her firſt Sutor, and the firſt that miſt her:</l>
                  <l>And though he promiſ'd that the <hi>Pope</hi> by Bull</l>
                  <l>Should licenſe it, <hi>SHEE</hi> held it but a Gull</l>
                  <l>For how can <hi>Pope</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Yet his Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts ſay;</hi> Benè diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſal Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa contra Apoſtolum Extrae. de Renunc. Ca. poſt tranſlatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> with Gods owne Law diſpence?</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1319:7"/>
                  <l>Was it not time ſuch <hi>Popes</hi> to cudgell hence?</l>
                  <l>Thus Her impregnable Virginity,</l>
                  <l>Throughout the World Her Fame did dignify.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And this may be a Document to all,</l>
                  <l>The Pearle of <hi>Chaſtity</hi> not to let fall:</l>
                  <l>Into the filthy durt of foule Deſires,</l>
                  <l>Which Satan kindles with his Hell-bred fires:</l>
                  <l>For whether it be termed Virginall</l>
                  <l>In Virgins, or in Wiues ſtil'd Conjugall,</l>
                  <l>Or Viduall in Widdowes, God reſpects</l>
                  <l>All equally, and all a like affects.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And here I may not ſilent overpaſſe</l>
                  <l>That Noble Lady of the Court, which was</l>
                  <l>Sollicited by <hi>TAXIS</hi> that great <hi>DON,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Embaſſador for Spaine (when <hi>SHEE</hi> was gone)</l>
                  <l>Who to obtaine his will,<note place="margin">Primo
<hi>Iacobi.</hi>
                     </note> gaue her a Chaine</l>
                  <l>Of moſt rare Orient Pearle, hoping to gaine</l>
                  <l>That Worthy Lady to his Luſt;<note place="margin">Related by theho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notable K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. and Baronet, <hi>SIR Richard Hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghton</hi> of
<hi>Hough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> But <hi>Shee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That well perceiu'd his Spaniſh Policy,</l>
                  <l>His faire Chaine kept, but his foule Offer ſcorn'd,</l>
                  <l>That ſought (thereby) her Husband to haue horn'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>TAXIS</hi> repulſt, ſent to Her for his Chaine,</l>
                  <l>But (as a <hi>Trophie</hi>) <hi>Shee</hi> did it retaine;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which Noble Preſident may all excite,</l>
                  <l>To keepe this Pearle, which is ſo Orient bright.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="prudence" type="part">
               <head>The third Pearle. <hi>PRVDENCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOW prudent was her Government appeard</l>
                  <l>By her wiſe Counſels, by the which <hi>SHEE</hi> ſteer'd,</l>
                  <l>In the moſt dangerous Times that ever were,</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1319:7"/>
                  <l>Since King or Queene did Crowne in England weare.</l>
                  <l>Her choice of Famous Councellers did ſhow,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Shee</hi> did all the Rules of Prudence know:</l>
                  <l>For though her Wit and Spirit were divine;</l>
                  <l>Counſels (<hi>Shee</hi> knew) were beſt, where more combine:</l>
                  <l>That for Experience and deepe Policy</l>
                  <l>Are well approved; whoſe Fidelity</l>
                  <l>Retaines them in the bonds of Loyall Loue,</l>
                  <l>And no great Penſions from their Prince can moue.</l>
                  <l>Thus rul'd <hi>SHEE</hi> prudently with all her power,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Argus</hi> Eyes foreſeeing every houre</l>
                  <l>All dangers imminent, leaſt any harmes</l>
                  <l>Should vs befall by Spaniſh Arts or Armes:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Gift in her was much more emminent,</l>
                  <l>In that it is ſo rarely incident</l>
                  <l>To our weake Sex: And as a precious ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Deepe ſet in Gold, ſhines fairer, then alone,</l>
                  <l>Or ſet in Lead; ſo did all Graces ſhine</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Her</hi> more gloriouſly, becauſe Divine:</l>
                  <l>For Kings are Gods, and Queenes are Goddeſſes</l>
                  <l>On Earth, whoſe facred Vertues beſt expreſſes</l>
                  <l>Their true Divinitie: wherein, if <hi>WEE</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Them imitate, tis our Felicity.</l>
                  <l>This Pearle of Prudence then, <hi>Wee</hi> all ſhould prize</l>
                  <l>Moſt highly, for it doth indeede compriſe</l>
                  <l>All Morall Vertues, which are reſident</l>
                  <l>In that bleſt ſoule, where this is preſident.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="temperance" type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1319:8"/>
               <head>The fourth Pearle. <hi>TEMPERANCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THE Golden Bridle of <hi>Bellerephon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is Temperance, by which our Paſſion,</l>
                  <l>And Appetite we conquer and ſubdue</l>
                  <l>To Reaſons Regiment: elſe may we rue</l>
                  <l>Our yeelding to Mens <hi>Syren</hi>-blandiſhments,</l>
                  <l>Which are attended with ſo foule Events.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Pearle in <hi>HER</hi> was ſo conſpicuous,</l>
                  <l>As that the<note n="*" place="margin">Edward</note> King Her Brother ſtill did vſe,</l>
                  <l>To ſtile <hi>HER</hi> His ſweete Siſter Temperance;</l>
                  <l>By which Her much admir'd Selfe-governance,</l>
                  <l>Her Paſſions ſtill <hi>SHEE</hi> checkt, and ſtill
<hi>SHEE</hi> made</l>
                  <l>The World aſtoniſht, that ſo vndiſmaid</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SHEE</hi> did with equall Tenor ſtill proceede</l>
                  <l>In one faire courſe, not ſhaken as a reed:</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Semper eadem.</note>But built vpon the Rocke of Temperance:</l>
                  <l>Not daz'd with feare, not maz'd with any Chance;</l>
                  <l>Not wiih vaine Hope (as with an emptie Spoone)</l>
                  <l>Fed or allur'd to caſt beyond the Moone:</l>
                  <l>Not with raſh Anger to precipitate,</l>
                  <l>Not fond to loue, nor too too prone to hate:</l>
                  <l>Not charm'd with Paraſites, or <hi>Syrens</hi> Songs,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hearts are poiſon'd, though their ſugred Tongues</l>
                  <l>Sweare, vow, and promiſe all Fidelity,</l>
                  <l>When they are bruing deepeſt Villany.</l>
                  <l>Not led to vaine or too profuſe Expence,</l>
                  <l>Pretending thereby State Magnificence:</l>
                  <l>Not ſpending on theſe momentany pleaſures</l>
                  <l>Her precious Time: but deeming her beſt Treaſures</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1319:8"/>
                  <l>Her Subiects Loue,<note place="margin">Omnibus incutiens bland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> per pectorae amorem.</note> which <hi>SHEE</hi> ſo well preſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>By ſweete and milde Deameanor, as it ſeru'd</l>
                  <l>To guard <hi>Her</hi> ſurer, then an Armie Royall;</l>
                  <l>So true their Loues were to Her, and ſo Loyall:</l>
                  <l>O Golden Age! O bleſt and happie Yeares!</l>
                  <l>O Muſicke ſweeter then that of the Spheares!</l>
                  <l>When Prince and people mutually agree</l>
                  <l>In ſacred Concord, and ſweete Symphonie!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="clemency" type="part">
               <head>The fift Pearle <hi>CLEMENCY.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>HER</hi> Royall <hi>Clemency</hi> comes next in view,</l>
               <l>The Vertue which in <hi>HER</hi> did moſt renew</l>
               <l>The Image of <hi>Her</hi> Maker, who in that</l>
               <l>Exceeds himſelfe, and doth commiſerate</l>
               <l>His very Rebells, lending them the light</l>
               <l>Of Sunne and Moone, and all thoſe Diamonds bright.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">monſtrae, teterrima monſtra.</note>So did <hi>ELIZA</hi> caſt <hi>Her</hi> Golden Rayes</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Clemency,</hi> on thoſe which many wayes</l>
               <l>Tranſgreſt <hi>Her</hi> Lawes, and ſought to vndermine</l>
               <l>The Church and State, and did with Spaine combine.</l>
               <l>And though by Rigor of the Law <hi>Shee</hi> might</l>
               <l>Not wronging them, haue taken all <hi>Her</hi> right</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Her</hi> Innate and princely <hi>Clemencie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mov'd Her to pardon their Delinquencie,</l>
               <l>Which ſought Her Gracious Mercy, and repented</l>
               <l>Their Miſdemeanors, and their Crimes lamented.</l>
               <l>So doth the the Kingly Lyon with his foe,</l>
               <l>Which once proſtrate, he ſcornes to worke his woe.</l>
               <l>So did this Vertues ſacred Auri flame,</l>
               <l>Immortalize our Great <hi>ELIZA'S</hi> Name.</l>
            </div>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1319:9"/>
            <div n="justice" type="part">
               <head>The ſixt Pearle; <hi>IVSTICE.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>HER <hi>Iuſtice</hi> next appeares, which did ſupport</l>
               <l>Her Crowne, and was her Kingdomes ſtrongeſt Fort.</l>
               <l>For ſhould not Lawes be executed well,</l>
               <l>And Malefactors curb'd, a very Hell</l>
               <l>Of all Confuſion and diſorder would</l>
               <l>Among all States enſue. Hereto vnfold</l>
               <l>The exemplary Penalties of thoſe,</l>
               <l>Which to the Realme were knowne, and mortall Foes:</l>
               <l>And as ſome putrid members par'd away,</l>
               <l>Leaſt their tranſcendent Villany ſhould ſway</l>
               <l>Others to like Diſloyalty; would aske</l>
               <l>A larger Volume, and would be a Taske</l>
               <l>Vnfit for Feminine hands, which rather loue</l>
               <l>To write of pleaſing ſubiects, then approue</l>
               <l>The moſt deſerved ſlaughtering of any;</l>
               <l>Which juſtly cannot argue Tyranny.</l>
               <l>For though the <hi>Pope</hi> haue lately ſent from Rome,</l>
               <l>Strange Bookes and pictures painting out the Doome</l>
               <l>Of his pretended Martyrs: as that they</l>
               <l>Were baited in Beares skins, and made a prey</l>
               <l>To wilde Beaſts, and had Bootes with boiling Lead</l>
               <l>Drawne on their Legges, and Hornes nail'd to their head;</l>
               <l>Yet all our Britiſh world knowes theſe are fables,</l>
               <l>Chimaera's, Phantaſm's, Dreames, and very Bables</l>
               <l>For Fooles to play with: and right Goblin-Sprights,</l>
               <l>Wherewith our Nurſes oft their Babes affrights.</l>
               <l>His Holineſſe theſe Martyrdomes may adde</l>
               <l>To the <hi>Golden Legend;</hi> for they are as madde,</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1319:9"/>
               <l>That firſt invented them, as<note n="*" place="margin">Vappa Voragino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</note> he that write</l>
               <l>That braneleſſe Booke: and yet ſome credit it.</l>
               <l>For Cruelty and fond Credulity,</l>
               <l>Are the maine Pillers of Romes Hierarchy.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="fortitude" type="part">
               <head>The ſeventh Pearle. <hi>FORTITVDE.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>THIS goodly Pearle, is that rare Fortitude,</l>
               <l>Wherewith this Sacred Princeſſe was endu'd.</l>
               <l>Witneſſe Her braue vndaunted Looke, when <hi>Parry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was fully bent <hi>SHEE</hi> ſhould by him miſcarry:</l>
               <l>The Wretch confeſt, that <hi>Her</hi> Great Majeſtie</l>
               <l>With ſtrange amazement did him terrifie.</l>
               <l>So Heavenly-Gracefull, and ſo full of Awe,</l>
               <l>Was that Majeſticke Queene, which when ſome ſaw,</l>
               <l>They thought an Angell did appeare: <hi>SHEE</hi> ſhon</l>
               <l>So bright, as <hi>None elſe</hi> could Her
<hi>Paragon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But that which doth beyond all Admiration</l>
               <l>Illuſtrate Her, and in Her, this whole Nation;</l>
               <l>Is that Heroicke March of Her's and Speech</l>
               <l>At <hi>Tilbury,</hi> where <hi>Shee</hi> did All beſeech</l>
               <l>Brauely to fight for England, telling them</l>
               <l>That what their Fortune was, ſhould Hers be then.</l>
               <l>And that with full Reſolue <hi>Shee</hi> thither came,</l>
               <l>Ready to win, or quite to looſe the Game.</l>
               <l>Which words deliver'd in moſt Princely ſort,</l>
               <l>Did animate the Army, and report</l>
               <l>To all the World Her Magnanimity,</l>
               <l>Whoſe haughtie Courage nought could terrify.</l>
               <l>Well did <hi>Shee</hi> ſhew, Great <hi>Henry</hi> was Her Sire,</l>
               <l>Whom Europe did for Valor moſt admire,</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:1319:10"/>
               <l>'Mongſt all the Warlike Princes which were then</l>
               <l>Enthronized with Regall Diadem.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="science" type="part">
               <head>The Eight Pearle. <hi>SCIENCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>AMong the Vertues Intellectuall,</l>
               <l>The Van is lead by that we <hi>Science</hi> call;</l>
               <l>A Pearle more precious then th' <hi>Aegyptian Queene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quaft off to <hi>Anthony;</hi> of more Eſteeme</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Indian Gold,</hi> or moſt reſplendent Gemmes,</l>
               <l>Which raviſh vs with their tranſlucent Beames.</l>
               <l>How many Arts and Sciences did decke</l>
               <l>This <hi>HEROINA?</hi> Who ſtill had at becke</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> and the <hi>Graces,</hi> when that
<hi>Shee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Gaue Audience in State and Maieſtie:</l>
               <l>Then did the Goddeſſe <hi>Eloquence</hi> inſpire</l>
               <l>Her Royall Breſt: <hi>Apollo</hi> with his <hi>Lyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ne're made ſuch Muſicke; On her Sacred Lips</l>
               <l>Angells enthron'd, moſt Heavenly <hi>Manna</hi> ſips.</l>
               <l>Then might you ſee her <hi>Nectar-flowing</hi> Veine</l>
               <l>Surround the Hearers; in which ſugred Streame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>SHEE</hi> able was to drowne a World of men,</l>
               <l>And drown'd, with Sweetnes to reuiue agen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alaſco,</hi> the Embaſſador <hi>Polonian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who perorated like a meere <hi>Slavonian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in rude rambling <hi>Rhetoricke</hi> did roule,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>SHEE</hi> did with <hi>Atticke Eloquence</hi> controule</l>
               <l>Her Speeches to our <hi>Academians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Well ſhew'd <hi>Shee</hi> knew among <hi>Athenians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How to deliver ſuch well-tuned Words,</l>
               <l>As with ſuch Places punctually accords.</l>
               <l>But with what <hi>Oratory</hi>-raviſhments,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1319:10"/>
               <l>Did <hi>Shee</hi> imparadiſe Her <hi>Parliaments?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her laſt moſt Princely Speech doth verify,</l>
               <l>How highly <hi>Shee</hi> did England dignify.</l>
               <l>Her Loyall Commons how did <hi>Shee</hi> embrace,</l>
               <l>And entertaine with a moſt Royall Grace?</l>
            </div>
            <div n="patience" type="part">
               <head>The ninth Pearle; <hi>PATIENCE.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>NOW come we Her rare <hi>Patience</hi> to diſplay;</l>
               <l>Which, as with pureſt Gold, did paue her way</l>
               <l>To Englands Crowne; for when her Siſter rul'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee</hi> was with many great Afflictions ſchoold:</l>
               <l>Yet all the while Her <hi>Mot,</hi> was <hi>Tanquam Ovis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor could her Enemies proue ought amiſſe</l>
               <l>In Her, although they thirſted for her bloud,</l>
               <l>Reputing it once ſhed, their Soveraigne good.</l>
               <l>Sometime, in Priſon this ſweere <hi>Saint</hi> was pent,</l>
               <l>Then haſtily away <hi>Shee</hi> thence was ſent</l>
               <l>To Places more remote, and all her Friends</l>
               <l>Debar'd acceſſe; and none but ſuch attends,</l>
               <l>As ready were with poiſon, or with knife,</l>
               <l>To Sacrifice this Sacred Princeſſe life,</l>
               <l>At bloudy <hi>Bonners</hi> becke, or <hi>Gardiners</hi> nod;</l>
               <l>Had they not bin pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ented by that GOD,</l>
               <l>Who did <hi>Suſanna</hi> from the <hi>Elders</hi> free,</l>
               <l>And at the laſt, gaue her, her Liberty.</l>
               <l>Thus by her patient bearing of the Croſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee</hi> reaped greateſt Gaine from greateſt Loſſe,</l>
               <l>(For he that looſeth his bleſt Liberty,</l>
               <l>Hath found a very Hell of miſery:)</l>
               <l>By many Croſſes thus <hi>Shee</hi> got the Crowne;</l>
               <l>To Englands Glory, and her great Renowne.</l>
            </div>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1319:11"/>
            <div n="bounty" type="part">
               <head>The tenth Pearle. <hi>BOVNTY.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS Roſe and Lillie challenge cheefeſt place,</l>
                  <l>For milke-white Luſtre, and for Purple Grace:</l>
                  <l>So Englands Roſe and Lillie, had no Peere,</l>
                  <l>For Princely Bounty ſhining every-where.</l>
                  <l>This made her Fame with Golden Wings to fly</l>
                  <l>About the World, aboue the Starry Sky.</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe <hi>France, Portugall, Virginia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Germany, Scotland, Ireland, Belgia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe Provinces and Princes found her Aid</l>
                  <l>On all Occaſions; which ſore diſmaid</l>
                  <l>Spaines King whoſe <hi>Europaean</hi> Monarchy,</l>
                  <l>Could never thriue during her Soveraignty;</l>
                  <l>So did <hi>Shee</hi> beare him with her Diſtaffe, ſo</l>
                  <l>By<note n="*" place="margin">Eliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethae fuit Terrae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gina Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſquè. <hi>Primo</hi> Iacobi.</note> Sea and Land <hi>Shee</hi> him did ouerthrow;</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſo that Tyrant on his knees <hi>Shee</hi> brought</l>
                  <l>That of braue England Peace he * beg'd, and thought</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe moſt happie, that by begging ſo</l>
                  <l>Preſerv'd all Spaine from Beggery and Woe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here all amaz'd my <hi>Muſe</hi> ſets vp her reſt,</l>
                  <l>Adoring <hi>HER</hi> was ſo Divinely bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>At nos horrifico cinefactam TE propè Buſto,</l>
                     <l>Inſatiabiliter deſlebimus, aeternumque.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1319:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
